The final episode's storyboards were rejected.
（水山）
最終話のコンテが
ボツ…
Does the director know?
（葛城(かつらぎ)）
監督には？
（渡辺(わたなべ)）
まだ話してません
No, I haven't told him yet.
The scenario has to be rewritten this far in?!
今からシナリオ書き直し？
Can we really air it in five weeks?
それで５週後 放送できる？
Sure.
（渡辺）できます
（葛城）間に合う？
Will it be ready?
We'll get it ready.
（渡辺）
間に合わせます
I'll prepare a recap episode just in case.
一応 準備しとく？　総集編
Please do.
（渡辺）
お願いします
Yeah, can you believe it?
（木下(きのした)）
そうなんだよ～
原作 まだ完結してないからさ～
The source material hasn't finished yet, you see.
（携帯電話のバイブ音）
（木下）ありあは飛んだけど…
Aria flies again, but it's more like a new beginning than an ending.
Director, your phone's been ringing for a while now.
（藤）
監督 さっきから
携帯 何度も鳴ってますよ
いいの いいの　後で…
It's fine! I'll call back later.
（中田）
ああ 監督ですか
いらっしゃいますよ
Ah, the director? Yeah, he's here.
Anyway, the ending is really important!
Just think about it!
Yes, sir!
かしこまりです！
食べて…
You eat it and...
Hm, the taste of soy sauce with ginger...
これはショウガの効いた
しょうゆ味だな
このショウガにこだわって
The ginger is highlighted, fitting in like the piece that completes this dish.
そこがポイントだなって
味わったところで 料理として…
（中田）監督 ちょっといいですか
（木下）えっ？
Just a moment, director.
What are you doing?
いきなり なんだよ～
It's a game!
ゲームですよ ゲーム
Fun with blindfolds, like they do with geishas?
あっ 目隠し鬼的な
芸者遊び？
Make sure you keep that on!
まだ取っちゃダメですよ
Will do!
は～い！
Is it just me, or did we just step outside?
Bar Shusen
Chicken
（木下）
気のせいかも
しれないけど
外 出てない？
It's just you.
（中田）
気のせいです
Take a seat here.
（中田）
はい 座ってください
Okay!
（木下）
は～い！
Strapping on your harness!
（中田）
ハーネスつきま～す
（木下）
は～い！
Sure!
Destination: Musashino Animation!
目的地 武蔵野(むさしの)アニメーション
発進！
Depart!
Wait, what's going on?!
えっ？　なな… なんなの？
Huh? Miyamori?
あれ？　宮森(みやもり)？　なんで？
But why?
We're going to the studio.
（あおい）会社に戻ります
（木下）えっ？
Episode 10's rush check is waiting for you.
定例の
10話のラッシュがありますから
（木下）
だましたな～！
You tricked me!
Flip the Table 2
You can't tell me you want to meet out of the blue.
Funny thing is, I've got no time.
（茶沢(ちゃざわ)）
いや～ いきなり会いたいって
言われても
今 時間取れないんですよ～
変な話
Then we're heading on up.
We're outside the building right now.
（渡辺）
それでは
今から伺わせていただきます
下に来てるんで
Huh?
（茶沢）
はい？
What do you mean the storyboards are no-go?
（葛城）
茶沢さん
コンテがボツって どういう…
あれ？
ボツって言葉 知りません？
Huh? You don't know what "no-go" means?
We do.
知ってます
（茶沢）
だったら わざわざ聞かなくても
Then why'd you bother asking?
Chazawa-kun, what did Nogame-sensei say?
（半藤）
茶沢君
野亀(のがめ)先生は なんて言ってんの？
He was furious.
いや～ それが先生 カンカンでして
He said he can't accept that finale.
“あの最終回は認めない”
It has to be redone from scratch.
“全面的にやり直してください”
って おっしゃってるんですよ
But why now?
（渡辺）
どうして今頃になって…
Funny thing is, he just checked the storyboards.
今頃になってコンテを
確認されたからですね～ 変な話
Chazawa-san, you said that there was no problem and we could start production.
茶沢さん 進めていいって
おっしゃいましたよね
問題ないって
あれは“僕的には”の話
That was my personal opinion.
I never said that the author okayed it.
先生からオーケーが出たとは
ひと言も言ってません
（渡辺）なっ…
（茶沢）先生のご意見は別ですから
He happens to think differently.
Please, can't we proceed with what we have?
（葛城）
お願いします！
このまま いかせてもらうわけには
いきませんか
We've already done voice
recording for the final episode!
最終話は
もうアフレコも終わってるんです
If we have to redo it at this point,
the quality will suffer!
今から やり直してたら
間違いなくクオリティーが落ちます
It might not even make the scheduled airtime!
いや それどころか
放送も落ちるかもしれません
You're threatening us?
それ脅しっすか？
We've done everything in our power to have the plot, scenario, and storyboards confirmed.
こちらとしては
しかるべき手順を踏んで
プロットも シナリオも コンテも
全て確認をお願いしています
His opinion was not by any means ignored.
決して原作者の意向を無視して
作っているわけではありません
We would like to talk with the author directly.
あの できれば 先生と直接
お話しさせていただきたいんですが
おたくら
ゴッドに盾つく気ですか！
You want to face God, heretics?!
In this world, the author's word is everything!
この世界 原作者の言うことが
全てなんですよ！
Without Nogame-sensei,
3rd Wing wouldn't even exist!
野亀先生がいなければ
「サンジョ」という作品は
生まれてこなかったんです
いわば 先生は作品世界の創造主！
He's the creator of this franchise's world!
If God says no, that means no.
（半藤）
ゴッドがノーと言った以上
それはノーなんです
I hope you understand.
ご理解いただけますね
What exactly should this remake be like, then?
（葛城）
やり直すといっても
具体的には どのようにすれば…
"No-go" isn't enough of a guide.
（渡辺）
ボツだけでは分かりません
I'll ask Nogame-sensei.
じゃあ 野亀先生に聞いてみます
Redo the final episode now?!
（あおい）
今から最終回を作り直す？
We tried everything.
（葛城）
粘ったんだよ～
It just wasn't enough.
でもね ダメだった
Completely from scratch?
（あおい）
あの… 全面的にですか？
We're waiting for directions from Nogame-sensei now.
野亀先生から
直しの指示が来る
Once that comes, we'll see if it's possible at all.
それを見て
対応できるか考えよう
Then the work...
じゃあ 作業は…
Stop all work on the final episode.
（渡辺）最終回は全部ストップだ
（ロロ･ミムジー）えっ？
Who are you?
（ミムジー）
あなたは？
I am the author.
（原作者）
予は原作者であるぞ
さ～て ここで―
You shall face my final quiz.
ラストクイ～ズ！
（ミムジー･ロロ）えっ？
Which way will the final episode go?
（原作者）
最終回は どっちかな～？
（原作者）チッチッチッ…
（ロロ･ミムジー）う～ん こっち！
That way!
Wrong!
（原作者）ハズレ～！
（ロロ･ミムジー）落ちる～！
Mayday!
（井口(いぐち)）
分かった
12話まで やれる作業はやっておく
Got it.
I'll do everything I can up to episode 12.
But are we gonna be okay?
でも大丈夫かな…
Worrying will not improve the situation.
（小笠原(おがさわら)）
不安になっても状況は変わりません
Brace for the worst possible scenario,
and prepare to struggle.
あらゆる最悪を想定しつつ
喜楽に構えましょう
Dear Chazawa
An ending where Aria flies again
is out of the question.
Follow the novels
and end it with Catherine's death.
Nogame
"An ending where Aria flies again is out of the question.
（あおい）
“ありあがまた飛ぶようになるのは
絶対ＮＧです”
Follow the novels and end it with Catherine's death.
“原作どおり
キャサリンが死んだところで”
“終わりにしてください　野亀”
Nogame."
So the main character will have to stay depressed for the final episode?
（みどり）
主人公が挫折したままで
最終回を迎えることになりますね
It's an incredibly bad way to end.
究極のバッドエンドだな
（舞茸(まいたけ)）
だから アニメオリジナルの結末を
作ったんじゃないですか
That's why we wrote the anime-original ending we did in the first place.
Now the author says our original contribution isn't acceptable.
でも そのオリジナル部分が
ダメだって言ってるからな…
I understand how he feels, of course,
原作者の気持ちも
分からないではないけど
but it's off-putting for someone who watches the anime first.
でも アニメから入った人は―
納得できないだろうな
（ノック）
Hang in there. Sounds like we're in a pickle.
（丸川(まるかわ)）
お疲れさま　大変だね
Have some of these.
これ食べて
Rice balls with emoji?
（あおい）
顔のおにぎりですか
Thank you.
いただきます
Good luck.
（丸川）
じゃあ よろしくね
What do you say, director?
（舞茸）
監督はどうなんですか？
Aria finding the meaning in flying...
あの…
ありあが飛ぶ意味を見つける
That's what you wanted to show in this production, right?
それが この作品で
監督がやりたかったことですよね
I'll have to write an ending where Aria doesn't fly again, I guess.
とりあえず書くしかないでしょうね
ありあが飛ばないエンドで
She came back with the last of her strength.
（ありあ）
最後の力を振り絞って
戻ってきたんだ
She...
（ノア）
ここに…
She was really excited to come back.
“ここに帰ってきたかったんだね”
“うん”
ウ～！
“第307飛行隊 発進準備！”
Squadron 307, prepare to scramble!
I repeat! Squadron 307, prepare to scramble!
（基地内アナウンス）
繰り返す 第307飛行隊 発進準備！
Time to go.
（タチアナ）
行くよ
Right. Let's go.
（ノア）
そうだね　行こう
But I can't.
（ありあ）
無理だ
There's no way I can fly.
私は… 飛べない…
The End
That's terrible and anticlimactic!
なんだ
このアンチクライマックス！
It's like some ATG movie.
（山田(やまだ)）
ＡＴＧ映画みたいですね
How'd it go? Did you decide on how we should go?
（安藤(あんどう)）
あっ どうなりました？
（佐藤(さとう)）
方向 決まったんですか？
It has to follow the original.
うん 原作準拠になった
（太郎(たろう)）
え～！
俺が監督だったら絶対折れないな
If I was the director, I'd put up a fight!
I'd defend my ending to the bitter end.
自分の決めた結末は
絶対に守ってみせる
（矢野(やの)）
それが放送できなくても？
Even if it meant not being able to air it?
We can't make something the author doesn't approve of.
原作者の了承がないものを
作るわけにはいかないでしょ
Giving up won't solve anything!
妥協してどうするんすか！
Arguing over two extreme opinions won't solve anything either.
極端な意見がぶつかったままだと
何もまとまらないだろ
This isn't the first of Nogame's work to get an anime adaptation, by the way.
（安藤）
そういえば 野亀先生の原作
アニメ化されるの２度目ですよね
Yeah. There was that race car show called Sailor Uniforms and F3.
うん
確か「セーラー服とＦ３(スリー)」っていう
自動車レースものだったかな
ああ あったね
I remember that.
Nogame-sensei wrote that too?
（太郎）
あれ 野亀先生だったんだ
It was hell.
（平岡(ひらおか)）
さんざんだった
I only ran an outsourced episode, but still.
（平岡）
俺はグロスの
制作進行だっただけだけどさ
How was it hell?
どう さんざんだったんですか？
I loved the original, so I was stoked to work on it.
俺 この原作 大好きで
関わるの楽しみにしてたんだけど
蓋を開けたら…
But then...
The protagonist's character was off,
主人公のキャラは改変
and they threw her in a bikini for races.
レーサーなのに なぜか水着で運転
It was nonstop ridiculous twists.
ありえないことの連続
The story had nothing to do with the original.
原作を無視したストーリー
The quality of the show and the ratings were terrible.
クオリティーも低くて
評判も悪かった
Even the author got some backlash.
原作者までたたかれて…
（佐藤）
ホントさんざんだったんですね
That does sound like hell.
Sorry to say this after you've written the scenario,
（木下）
書いてきてもらって
申し訳ないけど…
but I want to end it with some hope.
やっぱり
希望を持った終わり方にしたい
そりゃあ 僕だって そうしたいよ
I'd prefer that too myself.
（木下）
原作者との交渉の余地は？
Can't we negotiate with the author?
The publisher won't let us talk to him, since "it's unnecessary."
出版社サイドが
必要ないって会わせてくれない
Kinoshita-kun, may I have a second?
木下君 ちょっと
（丸川）
監督ってさ
どういう仕事だと思う？
What do you think is the director's job?
Huh?
If this were a ship?
（丸川）
船で言えば？
The captain.
船長
On a tank?
（丸川）戦車で言えば？
（木下）車長
The commander.
A plane?
（丸川）飛行機なら？
（木下）機長
The pilot.
That's right.
You steer the staff towards the destination.
That's the director's job.
目的地に向かって
みんなを導くのが監督なんだよね
I know.
自覚してます
If you reach it, you earn the sense of fulfillment, joy, and pride from a job well done.
（丸川）
そこに たどり着ければ
いい仕事をしたという高揚感と
満足と誇りが手に入るはずだ
Everyone believes that. That's why they work so hard.
みんな そう信じて
惜しみなく働いている
They sacrifice a good portion of their lives for the show.
人生の多くの時間を
作品にささげてる
The director's destination has to be one that satisfies both the crew and the viewers.
監督が目指す場所は
最後に 作ってる人も見ている人も
幸せになれる場所じゃないかな
Remember? Win-win!
ほら 言ってたじゃない
ウィン ウィン
Let's take off!
さあ テークオフ！
Win-win!
（丸川･木下）
ウィ～ン ウィ～ン ウィ～ン
（久乃木(くのぎ)）あっ！
（木下）ウ～
How do I reach my destination?
でも どうやったら
行きたい場所に行けるんだ？
Good afternoon!
（本田(ほんだ)）
こんにちは～
Ah, Honda-san!
あっ 本田さん
I brought a little present.
差し入れ 持ってきたよ
I'd like some Mont Blanc. You have any?
俺 今日は
モンブランな気分なんすよね～
あるかな～？
（本田）
あるけど～ ダメだ
I do, but you can't have it.
Why? You meanie.
え～ ケチ
It's for a certain someone.
（本田）これは もう予約済み
（太郎）う～
Win...
（木下）
ウィ～ン
ああ もう どれもダメだな～
Nothing works!
（本田）
監督
Director!
I heard what happened. Sounds rough.
聞きましたよ 大変ですね
フンッ
痩せた本田君なんか見たくない
I don't wanna see you and your skinny self.
すっかり見違えちゃって
I can barely recognize you.
I may not look it, but I actually feel fit on the inside.
俺は見た目はこんなだけど
心はゲッソリだよ
What's that phrase for times like this?
こういう時のこと
なんて言うんだっけ
Oh yeah. "I'm out of—
そうだ　万策…
No, you're not.
尽きてません！
For Director Kinoshita
It's huge!
大っき～い！
あ～ん
ん～ 甘～い！
So sweet!
It's delicious, Honda-kun!
おいしいよ 本田君
As long as there's fried chicken and
Mont Blanc in the world, I'll be fine!
俺 この世に
から揚げとモンブランがあれば
それだけで生きていけるよ～
Did that get things moving in your head?
（本田）
少しは
頭が回るようになりましたか？
I said in your head! Think!
（本田）
そうじゃありません
考えてください　どうするべきか
What are you going to do?
But I'm really out of—
でも 万策…
尽きてません！
No, you're not!
Trust me, I've been out of ideas plenty of times.
あれだけ万策尽きた僕が
断言するんです
I know what it's like!
間違いありません！
If I could just talk to the author myself...
せめて原作者と話し合えれば…
But I don't know how to contact him.
でも 連絡先も分からないしな～
Isn't that his email?
（木下）
おっ よし！
Score!
Please forgive my rudeness for contacting you directly.
（木下）
突然 メールを差し上げるご無礼を
お許しください
I am the director of the 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing anime adaptation, Kinoshita Seiichi.
「第三飛行少女隊」の監督を
させていただいております―
木下誠一(せいいち)です
I would like to consult you directly
regarding the final episode's contents.
最終回の内容について
ぜひ 野亀先生に
直接 お目にかかって
ご相談させていただきたいと
思っております
May I have some of your precious time?
I look forward to hearing from you.
先生のご都合を
お伺いしたいのですが
よろしくお願いいたします
Send.
Send
送信！
Is he even going to respond?
返事くれるかな～
He doesn't seem like the social type.
原作者 人嫌いみたいだしな～
You've got mail.
Reply
Reply All
Forward
Nogame Takezou
Regarding the final episode of 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
To                Kinoshita Seiichi
I'm Nogame.
Understood. Please come to the 35th floor meeting room of Nighthawk Publishing
at noon on November 30th. I will be waiting.
（木下･本田）おお！
（本田）早い！
That was fast!
Honda-kun! Thank you so much!
（木下）本田君 ありがとう！
（本田）いえ
No problem.
I hereby dub this day Big Mont Blanc Day
and carve it into my memory forever!
僕は この日を
“ビッグモンブランデー”と呼んで
永遠に忘れない！
President,
（木下）
社長 いってきます
I'm off.
Good luck.
うん 頑張ってね
It's dangerous to go alone.
あっ そうだ　ちょっと待って
Take this battle suit.
（丸川）
はい 勝負服
Nighthawk
Publishing HQ
Take care!
お気をつけて
Excuse me, sir, but you're not allowed in here!
（受付嬢）
お客様 困ります！
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Entrance Pass
Name: Kinoshita Seiichi
Nighthawk Publishing Inc.
This person is an employee of Nighthawk Publishing.
Director, where are you going?
監督 どこ行く気ですか
I'm here to see Nogame-sensei.
野亀先生に会いに来た
アポイントメントは取ってある
I have an appointment.
How dare you arrange that
without the editor's approval?!
編集部 通さねえで
何 勝手なことやってんだよ！
Funny thing is, you're not supposed to be here!
変な話 ここは
三下の来るところじゃねえんだ！
とっとと帰れ ぷる天野郎～！
Piss off, fatty!
Surge Belly!
波動腹(ばら)！
（作業員）
すみません 点検に入りま～す
is undergoing
maintenance
This elevator
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
Terribly sorry. We're doing maintenance.
is undergoing
maintenance
This elevator
is undergoing
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
maintenance
is undergoing
caused
This elevator
Sorry for the
inconvenience
is undergoing
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
is undergoing
maintenance
caused
This elevator
Sorry for the
inconvenience
is undergoing
maintenance
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
Sorry for the
inconvenience
maintenance
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
maintenance
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
This elevator
Sorry for the
caused
is undergoing
maintenance
inconvenience
This elevator
Sorry for the
caused
This elevator
is undergoing
Sorry for the
inconvenience
caused
maintenance
is undergoing
caused
Sorry for the
inconvenience
This elevator
is undergoing
caused
Sorry for the
is undergoing
maintenance
inconvenience
Sorry for the
What do we have here, director?
（半藤）
困りますな 監督
This is the top floor of Nighthawk Publishing.
ここは天下の夜鷹(よたか)書房 最上階
Only the chosen may tread these hallowed grounds.
選ばれし者しか
来ることができない場所
I will not resort to violence, but I will practice golf.
私は暴力は振るいません
ただ ゴルフの練習を
しているだけでね！
Gotcha!
やった～　ん？
Dragon Belly!
昇竜腹！
Who are you?
（尾之上(おのうえ)）
何者？
The animation director of 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing, Kinoshita Seiichi.
「第三飛行少女隊」
アニメーション監督
木下誠一
Hurricane Belly!
竜巻旋風腹！
What overwhelming force...
すごい気迫だ
You are Kinoshita Seiichi-san, correct?
（野亀）
木下誠一さんですね
（木下）
はい
Yes.
I have been waiting for you.
お待ちしておりました
野亀武蔵(たけぞう)です
I am Nogame Takezou.
Nogame Takezou
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing    Author
Please take a seat.
どうぞ お座りください
For the final episode...
（野亀）
それで最終回の件ですが
Please fix it.
直してください
I myself have not yet decided whether or not Aria will recover from the shock or choose a different path.
私もまだ ありあが立ち直るのか
別の道を選ぶのか
決めかねているのです
Aria has realized that unlike the others,
she doesn't have a reason to fly.
ありあは みんなと違って
自分が飛ぶ意味を
見いだせないことに気付きました
And then Catherine dies.
そこにキャサリンの死
She can't recover from that so easily.
容易に立ち直ることはできません
The series might continue with Aria never flying again
もしかしたら ありあが
飛ばないまま別の道を見つけて
and eventually finding a new path in life.
連載を終える道もあるかもしれない
It is a distinct possibility.
そう考えてもいます
For that reason, I would have you refrain from making Aria fly just to fit your production plans.
ですから アニメでも
ありあを制作側の都合で飛ばすのは
やめていただきたい
It can't end like that.
（木下）
それでは終われません
Isn't the goal of 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing to have the girls discover what it means for them to fly?
「第三飛行少女隊」のテーマは
少女たちにとって
飛ぶということは どういうことか
…ではないでしょうか
A powerful enemy.
強大な敵
圧倒的な戦力不足
The strength they lack.
The looming time limit of the world.
迫り来る世界のタイムリミット
Yet they fly again and again, and they continue to fight.
それでも
何度でも飛び 何度でも戦う
They have hope for the world that waits beyond the war.
その果てに訪れる世界に
希望を持っているのです
Aria must reach that place with her team by her side!
ありあは仲間たちとともに そこへ
たどり着かねばならないのです
That's how I wanted to depict them in this show.
僕は この作品で
そんな彼女たちの姿を
描きたいと思いました
The same goes every day in our own lives.
僕たちの毎日も
ありあたちと同じなんです
No matter how hard the fight is,
we have our friends supporting us.
どんな苦しい戦いも
仲間がいるから戦えるんです
That's why I'd like to make the main character, Aria, fly again no matter what.
だから 主人公には…
ありあには絶対飛んでほしい
仲間を信じて
She'll trust her friends.
それが 僕のたどり着きたい
最終回なんです！
That is the final episode I want to create.
Kinoshita-san...
木下さん
For you, your production team is the 3rd Girls' Fighter Wing, is it not?
あなたにとっては 制作チームが
「第三飛行少女隊」なんですね
That is why Aria must fly side by side with her team.
だから ありあは仲間を率いて
飛ばねばならない
I understand your sense of responsibility.
その責任感 よく伝わってきました
However, that does not apply to me.
でも私にとっては違います
How exactly?
どこが違うんでしょう？
The girls' battles with their enemies
ありあたちと敵との戦いは
are all a metaphor for my battle with the negativity directed at me.
私と 私を襲う
負のメタファーなのです
I have split my personality between the five members of the 3rd Wing.
「サンジョ」の５人には
私の人格を分け与えている
It is not the same team you envision.
あなたが考えるチームとは
違うのです
I see.
そっか
For you, 3rd Wing is not about the unity of a team,
野亀先生にとって「サンジョ」は
チームの団結ではなく
but a personal tale of death and rebirth.
個人的な死と再生の
物語なのかもしれませんね
That is why a sense of responsibility or guilt can't push Aria to the skies.
だから ありあは
責任感や罪の意識では飛べない
She can't fly unless her personal, internal issue is resolved.
ありあの個人的な内面の問題を
解決しないと飛べない… と
Exactly!
（野亀）
そうです
So Aria must find a reason of her own, right?
ありあが自分自身で飛ぶ意味を
見つけられないとダメなんですね
Yes, precisely!
そのとおりです
Unrelated to her hopes and dreams,
an objective reason for her to fly again.
夢や希望と無縁で
孤高なありあが飛ぶ意味
The utter lack of that is the issue she is facing.
その何もないところが
ありあの抱える
問題でもあるわけで… あっ
What if Aria found a dream or hope?
ありあに夢や希望が
生まれればいいのかもしれませんね
What if someone gave her some?
もしくは それを与えられる存在
Nogame-sensei.
（木下）
野亀先生
No need to address me so formally.
（野亀）
“先生”は やめてください
Nogame-san.
では 野亀さん
How about this? Aria wants to fulfill her promise to Catherine.
ありあがキャサリンとの約束を
果たすというのは？
The promise to see newborn calves.
生まれたての子牛を見ようという
Calves alone won't do, director Kinoshita.
いや～ 子牛だけでは弱いです
木下監督 もっと何か… 誰か…
We need more... Something, someone...
Catherine's parents?
キャサリンの両親
No. Something that would serve as a ray of hope.
いや もっと
希望の光になるような…
A little sister!
妹とか！
キャサリンの妹　いいですね！
Catherine's little sister! I like that!
うん　仲間の死を経て出会った
新しい命
A new life she discovers after the death of her friend.
A pure girl...
純粋な少女
少女が住む美しい故郷
The girl's beautiful motherland...
その全てが ありあにとって
守りたい存在となる！
All of that becomes what Aria wants to protect.
This is the first time I've found hope and joy in another company adapting my work.
私は今 初めて 自分の作品が
他者によって作られることに
希望と面白さを感じました
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
I'll send you the settings for
Catherine's little sister right away.
後で すぐに
キャサリンの妹の設定を送ります
Thank you!
お願いします！
I wish we had met sooner.
もっと早くに
お目にかかりたかったです
私もです
Likewise.
We asked the editor a number of times to allow us to see you.
ぜひ 野亀さんにお会いしたいと
編集部にお願いしていたんですが…
I heard nothing of that.
私は そうは聞いておりません
（木下）えっ？
（野亀）ということは…
Which means...
You damn fat-ass! Get out!
（茶沢）
こら～！
この腹ぷる野郎 出てけ 変な話！
Funny th—
変な話ではな～い！
It's not a funny thing!
（野亀）
茶沢さん
Chazawa-san, it seems you withheld a number of issues from me.
あなたが
いろいろと止めていたようですね
（半藤）
どういうことかね？　茶沢君
What is the meaning of this, Chazawa-kun?
Well, it would've been too much of a nuisance!
あ～ それはですね
いちいち面倒っていうか
I wanted to lighten his load a tad,
先生のご負担を
少しでも減らそうと
so, funny thing is, I tried to
intermediate and be like his shield!
わたくしが盾になって
先生をお守りしようと 変な話
変な話ではな～い！
It's not a funny thing!
It seems you're not suited to be his editor.
きみは先生の担当には
向いてないようだね
Very much agreed, manager.
まったくです 局長
あっ 監督 どうでした？
Director, how did it go?
Aria will fly again!
ありあは飛ぶ～！
Time to return to base!
さあ 基地に戻るぞ
Catherine's little sister
(about 13~15 years old)
> like an eagle chick
> she has good survival skills
What do you think, Kinoshita-san?
the wings are above her ears
color of an eaglet
Catherine's little sister
Additional scenes until Aria makes up her mind
Not only did she lose her reason to fly, Catherine died too.
Aria lost every bit of hope even to live, let alone to fly (the whole of part A)
Changes follow
Aria wanders.
She thought she wandered aimlessly,
but she ended up in Texas,
to fulfill her promise to Catherine.
Aria meets Catherine's little sister, Lucy.
Lucy's heard a lot about Aria from Catherine.
From listening to all those stories, Aria became aspiration for Lucy.
Surprisingly, Lucy knows of her sister's death,
and she has accepted reality calmly.
She lives on strong,
believing that a better world will come.
The light of the pure girl's faith starts to melt the ice
that held Aria's heart captive.
(No need to make the dialog between Aria and Lucy lengthy.
As long as it comes through
that Lucy becomes the very thing Aria wants to protect,
even just a few lines will do. Maitake-san, I'm counting on you.)
Continue to the pillar assault scene in part B.
（木下）
うん これでいけると思う
I think this will do!
There is an additional scene.
それで追加のシーンなんだけど…
What do you think, Maitake-san?
（あおい）
舞茸さん どうですか？
I can do it, but isn't the deadline tomorrow morning?
いいけど 今夜いっぱいか…
Do you have time after this?
この後 時間取れる？
Yeah, it's no problem!
（みどり）
えっ… あっ はい 大丈夫です！
I'll feed you the flow of events, and you write it down.
俺が口頭で流れを説明するから
それをまとめてくれる？
When you finish, send it to me. I'll fix it up by the morning.
書いたら送って
朝までに手入れるから
Okay!
分かりました
So let's hit a 24-hour restaurant.
（舞茸）
じゃ ファミレスでやるか
Roger!
了解っす！
I'll ask Iguchi-san to do Lucy's character designs!
井口さんにルーシーのキャラデも
お願いしてきます
If the new storyboards are done by Thursday...
木曜に
追加コンテ アップするとして…
They will be!
するよ～
Let's do video re-editing on Saturday.
土曜には再編集したいな
Voice recording on Sunday then?
アフレコは日曜かな
Only Aria and Lucy will have to be there.
ありあとルーシーだけで
オーケーだよね
Which brings us to Lucy's role.
で ルーシー役なんだけど
She's Catherine's sister, so they should sound similar, right?
キャサリンの妹だから やっぱり
面影が残ってるほうがいいよね
A younger Catherine, huh?
（木下）
キャサリンを
幼くした感じとなると…
Do you have the tapes from the auditions?
オーディションの音源 残ってる？
How's it going, Rii-chan?
（あおい）
りーちゃん お疲れさま
Going great!
あっ お疲れさまです
He let me write a line for the final version!
セリフ
１行だけ使ってもらえました
That's great!
よかったじゃん
Nogame-sensei approves of the scenario as well.
野亀先生からも
シナリオ オーケーの返事来たぞ
I'll ask the director to start on storyboards!
（あおい）
監督にコンテ入ってもらいます！
"The storyboards were great. I was touched. Nogame."
“コンテ 面白かったです”
“感動しました　野亀”　く～！
Fifty cuts out, a hundred new in.
（あおい）
50カット削って 100カット追加
We can't pull this off with only in-house staff. Time to find keyframers!
社内だけだと足りないから
原画マン 探さないとね
（佐藤･安藤）
はい！
On it!
Matsu
Tei
Food and drinks
Hello?
（しずか）
はい
bako chips
We need to trim out another three minutes?
（木下）
あと３分
切らなきゃいけないのか～
Ending
(90+00)
I don't want to cut anything anymore!
でも どこも削れないな～
（中林）
ありあが戦闘機に乗るシーンは
カットしたらどうですか？
How about the scene where Aria gets in the plane?
That's too abrupt!
（木下）
えっ いきなり？
Making it a surprise for the viewers would be fine too, I think.
（中林）
あえて視聴者に
驚きを取っておくのも
Nakabayashi Wataru
Video Editor
ありだと思います
That'd save us twenty seconds.
それで20秒切れます
And I tried splicing cuts of the earthbound Aria into the battle scene in part A.
（中林）
Ａパートの戦闘シーン
飛べないありあと
カットバックしてみたんですけど
Isn't the tempo a bit crazy?
テンポ 悪くなんない？
If we keep the cut-ins short, it should be fine enough.
カットバックするカットを
短めにすると
テンポは崩れないと思います
Let's go with that then.
（木下）
じゃ これでいこう
It's done.
（中林）
はい これで完尺です
We're done!
（木下）
終わった～！
We're not done. We've only just begun.
（佐藤）
終わってません
（安藤）
むしろ これからです
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
#13 extra voices recording
I'm Suzuki Kyouko. Thanks for having me again!
（鈴木(すずき)）
鈴木京子(きょうこ)です
よろしくお願いします！
Thanks for coming!
（あおい）
お疲れさまです
（木下）
今日はごめんね～ バタバタして
Sorry for calling you on such short notice.
いえ まだ ありあでいられて
うれしいです
I'm happy I can be Aria again!
（木下）
よろしくね～
Thanks!
Lucy's not here yet?
（葛城）
ルーシー まだ？
（しずか）
失礼します
Excuse me.
I'm here to play the part of Lucy.
ルーシー役で
参加させていただきます
I'm Sakaki Shizuka from Akaoni Production.
赤鬼(あかおに)プロダクションの
坂木(さかき)しずかと申します
Thank you for the opportunity!
よろしくお願いします
Thanks for coming!
（木下）
よろしく～
Ah, Sakaki-san.
あっ 坂木さん
Do you remember the way you did Catherine at the auditions?
オーディションで
キャサリンやってもらった時の
芝居 覚えてる？
Yes.
はい
"Thank you, Aria! You saved me!"
“ありがとね ありあ
私を助けてくれて”
That's it. Now make it a bit younger sounding.
（木下）
うん それより少しだけ幼く
Younger, but full of spirit and a will to live on the land.
幼いけど 大地に根ざして
生きてる感じが出るといいかな
Do it confidently!
自信持って やってください
I got it! I'll do my best!
分かりました
よろしくお願いします
I had her as one of the final
candidates for Catherine's role,
キャサリン役で
オーディション受けてもらった時も
最後まで引っ掛かってたんだけど
but she sounded a bit too young to fit.
ちょっと幼かったからな
She's a perfect match for this role, though.
でも今回は それがピッタリだよね
The farm scene, recording.
（稲浪(いななみ)）
じゃあ 牧場のシーン 本番いきます
Okay! We're ready!
（鈴木）はい！
（しずか）よろしくお願いします！
We're rolling.
（藤）
回りました
Lucy
（しずか）
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
Aria
Sorry! Are you Aria-san?
Lucy
（しずか）
あの もしかして やっぱり
ありあさん？
Lucy
You're just like she told me!
お姉ちゃんから
時々 聞いてたとおり！
Lucy
I'm Catherine's little sister! My name's Lucy!
あっ 私 キャサリンの妹です
Lucy
ルーシーです
What are you doing here?
どうして ここへ？
I came to see the calves.
（鈴木）
子牛を見に来た
（しずか）
子牛？
The calves?
I made a promise with Catherine.
（鈴木）
キャサリンと約束したから
（しずか）
あっ じゃあ こっちです！
Lucy
Then follow me!
My sister's left for somewhere far away,
お姉ちゃんは
遠いところへ行ってしまったけど
but I think I'll stay here forever.
私は ずっと ここにいようかな
Why?
（鈴木）
なぜ？
I'll raise lots of calves in the world you fight to protect!
ありあさんたちが戦って守る世界で
私は たくさんの子牛を育てるの
The world... we fight... to protect?
（鈴木）
私たちが戦って… 守る世界…
That's all I can do.
（しずか）
それが私にできること
That's my dream.
それが私の夢だから
（鈴木）あっ…
（しずか）ありあさん？
Aria-san?
I'm going back...
（鈴木）
戻る… この全てを守るために
so I can protect all of this.
Thank you, Aria-san!
ありがとう ありあさん
I'm now one step closer to my dream!
今 私…
少しだけ夢に近づきました！
That should be it for Lucy's scene.
（稲浪）
はい ルーシーのシーン
オーケーです
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございました
Hello! This is Musashino Animation!
Ah, Honda-san? Next week is video editing for 3rd Wing's final episode.
Seems like it's almost the same day it airs!
Shirobako, the final episode: "A Delivery Too Far Away."
A Delivery Too Far Away
（あおい）
はい 武蔵野アニメーションです
あっ 本田さん！
来週 「サンジョ」最終話の
Ｖ編なんですけど
放送当日になりそうで…
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」
最終回